Guide to the William Watts Ball papers, 1778-1952 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
William Watts Ball papers 1778-1952 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Ball, W. W. (William Watts), 1868-1952.
31 Linear Feet Approx. 26,000 Items
Newspaper editor and author.
Collection houses personal and political correspondence, financial and business papers, speeches, editorials, notes, printed materials, account books, a diary, photographs, and scrapbooks, documenting William Watts Ball's activities as editor of several South Carolina newspapers, including The State and the News and Courier, both of Columbia. Topics referred to include American and South Carolina politics in the 20th century; the South Carolina textile industry; African Americans in the South; the Great Depression and the Franklin D. Roosevelt administration; newspapers and the newspaper business; education in South Carolina; conditions and problems stemming from both World Wars; prohibition; states' rights; South Carolina social life and customs; Roman Catholicism in South Carolina; international issues; and business and family matters. Correspondents include J. J. McSwain, D. C. Heyward, John Gary Evans, John Hays Hammond, M. F. Ansel, David D. Wallace, James C. Hemphill, Ambrose E. Gonzales, Thomas R. Waring, Nathaniel B. Dial, James F. Byrnes, Ulrich B. Phillips, Josephus Daniels, Bernard M. Baruch, Warrington Dawson, Ellison D. Smith, Max Fleischman, Nicholas Roosevelt, Wendell Willkie, Frederick H. Allen, and Archibald Rutledge.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, collection may contain materials to which the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibilities and Privacy Rights form applies. Patrons must sign this form before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 24-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Watts Ball papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts from 1954 to 1986.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of personal and political correspondence, diaries, business papers, speeches, editorials, notes, printed matter, personal account books, memorandum books, photographic materials, and scrapbooks. The papers document a long period in Southern history, and reflect Ball's activities as editor of several newspapers, including The State, of Columbia, S.C., and the News and Courier, also of Columbia, S.C. The main group is concerned with national and South Carolina history for the first half of the 20th century. Topics referred to include American politics; the South Carolina textile industry; African Americans in the South; the depression and the F. D. Roosevelt administration; newspapers and the newspaper business; education in South Carolina; conditions and problems stemming from both World Wars; prohibition; states' rights; South Carolina social life and customs; Roman Catholicism in South Carolina; international issues; and general business and family matters.
A substantial portion of the papers consists of family correspondence containing information on school and college life; Hollywood in the 1930s and 1940s; social life and customs in Laurens, Charleston, and Columbia, South Carolina; and England, the Italian battlefront, and a journey across the Atlantic during World War II. Other letters come from editors, publishers, educators, politicians, financiers, and industrialists, principally from South Carolina, although some national figures are found. These correspondents include J. J. McSwain, D. C. Heyward, John Gary Evans, John Hays Hammond, M. F. Ansel, David D. Wallace, James C. Hemphill, Ambrose E. Gonzales, Thomas R. Waring, Nathaniel B. Dial, James F. Byrnes, Ulrich B. Phillips, Josephus Daniels, Bernard M. Baruch, Warrington Dawson, Ellison D. Smith, Max Fleischman, Nicholas Roosevelt, Wendell Willkie, Frederick H. Allen, and Archibald Rutledge.
Ball's financial papers, scattered throughout the collection, generally relate to real estate investments, stock holdings in textile mills, and the Depression as it affected his financial situation. A major part of the correspondence pertains to state and national politics. Letters discuss Tillmanism and Bleasism; the state primary system and election reform; state and national elections; opposition to the New Deal and the formation of the Southern Democratic Party; and other local, state, and national issues.
Material on race relations begins as early as 1916, but is particularly abundant from the 1930s onwards. Involved with the issue of states' rights versus federal control, the "Negro problem" includes the anti-lynching movement, enfranchisement and control of the African American vote, racial unrest, segregation, and other matters. The papers reveal Ball's interest in education, especially the development of schools of journalism, the expansion of the state-supported college system, the University of South Carolina, and the South Carolina School for the Deaf, Dumb, and Blind.
Other papers relate to Ball's editorship of various South Carolina newspapers, principally The State and the News and Courier, and to his publishing efforts. There is also material on the textile industry in South Carolina, labor unrest and unionization, prohibition, women's suffrage, the Great Depression, World Wars I and II, recollections by Ball and others of social life, customs and politics during the 1870s through the 1890s, the economic and industrial development of South Carolina, genealogy of the Watts and Ball families, and drafts and copies of speeches and editorials.
The photographic items include 34 black-and-white photographs (ca. 1840-1940), chiefly consisting of group and individual portraits of W. W. Ball's family, friends, and colleagues in journalism. There are several views of the Ball family's ancestral plantation home in Laurens, S.C. Volumes include family account books, 1911-1942, a memorandum book beginning in 1901; scrapbooks, 1893-1951; a digest of the military service of Frank Parker, 1894-1945; and Ball's diaries, 1916-1952.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Allen, Frederick Harold, 1890-
Ansel, Martin F., 1850-1945
Ball, W. W. (William Watts), 1868-1952
Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965
Byrnes, James F. (James Francis), 1882-1972
Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948
Dial, Nathaniel Barksdale, 1862-1940
Evans, John Gary, 1863-1942
Fleischmann, Max C. (Max Charles), 1877-1951
Gonzales, Ambrose Elliott, 1857-1926
Hammond, John Hays, 1855-1936
Hemphill, J. C. (James Calvin), 1850-1927
Heyward, Duncan Clinch, 1864-1943
Phillips, Ulrich Bonnell, 1877-1934
Rutledge, Archibald, 1883-1973
Smith, Ellison DuRant, 1866-1944
Wallace, David Duncan, 1874-1951
Waring, Thomas R.
Willkie, Wendell L. (Wendell Lewis), 1892-1944
News and Courier (Charleston, S.C.)
The State (Columbia, S.C.)
Education -- South Carolina
Journalism -- South Carolina
Journalists -- United States
Newspaper publishing -- South Carolina
Textile industry -- South Carolina
World War, 1914-1918 -- United States
World War, 1939-1945 -- United States
Laurens (S.C.) -- History
South Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
South Carolina -- Race relations
South Carolina -- Social life and customs
United States -- Foreign relations -- 20th century
United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century
Black-and-white photographs
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence and Other Papers, 1778-1952, (76 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1852-1905 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1906-1909 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1911 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1912-1913 Feb. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1913 Mar.-1914 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1916 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1919 June (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1919 July-1920 Feb. (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Mar.-Dec. (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1922 June (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1922 July-1923 Aug. (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1923 Sept.-1925 Aug. (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1925 Sept.-1926 Sept. (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1926 Oct.-1927 Aug. (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1927 Sept.-1928 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1931 (Box 19)
  - Correspondence, 1932 Jan.-June (Box 20)
  - Correspondence, 1932 July-Dec. (Box 21)
  - Correspondence, 1933 Jan.-Aug. (Box 22)
  - Correspondence, 1933 Sept.-1934 May (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1934 June-Dec. (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, 1935 Jan.-Sept. (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1935 Oct.-1936 June (Box 26)
  - Correspondence, 1936 July-1937 Feb. (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, 1937 Mar.-Aug. (Box 28)
  - Correspondence, 1937 Sept.-1938 Feb. (Box 29)
  - Correspondence, 1938 Mar.-Oct. (Box 30)
  - Correspondence, 1938 Nov.-1939 June (Box 31)
  - Correspondence, 1939 July-Dec. (Box 32)
  - Correspondence, 1940 Jan.-May (Box 33)
  - Correspondence, 1940 June-1941 Feb. (Box 34)
  - Correspondence, 1941 Mar.-Dec. (Box 35)
  - Correspondence, 1942 Jan.-July (Box 36)
  - Correspondence, 1942 Aug.-1943 Mar. (Box 37)
  - Correspondence, 1943 Apr.-Dec. (Box 38)
  - Correspondence, 1944 Jan.-June (Box 39)
  - Correspondence, 1944 July-Dec. (Box 40)
  - Correspondence, 1945 Jan.-Oct. (Box 41)
  - Correspondence, 1945 Nov.-1946 Oct. (Box 42)
  - Correspondence, 1946 Nov.-1947 (Box 43)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 44)
  - Correspondence, 1949 Jan.-Oct. (Box 45)
  - Correspondence, 1949 Nov.-1950 Apr. (Box 46)
  - Correspondence, 1950 May-1951 July (Box 47)
  - Correspondence, 1951 Aug.-1952 (Duplicate letters) (Box 48)
  - Correspondence, undated [1910-1919, 1920s] (Box 59)
  - Correspondence, undated [1920s] (Box 50)
  - Correspondence, undated [1930s] (Box 51)
  - Correspondence, undated [1930s, 1940s] (Box 52)
  - Correspondence, undated [1940s] (Box 53)
  - General papers, 1897-1952 [restrictions now lifted] (Box 54)
  - Legal papers, 1778-1951; Legislation (Box 55)
  - Financial papers, 1833-1919 (Box 56)
  - Financial papers, 1920-1952; Income tax (Box 57)
  - Writings, speeches, 1883-1929 (Box 58)
  - Writings, speeches, 1930-1952 (Box 59)
  - Writings, speeches, undated (Box 60)
  - Miscellany: report cards; genealogy (Box 61)
  - Miscellany: business reports, 1905-1924; greeting cards (Box 62)
  - Photographs (Box 63)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 64)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 65)
  - Printed materials (Box 66)
  - Printed materials (Box 67)
  - Volumes (Box 68)
    Notebooks, calendars, and other small volumes.
  - Volumes (Box 69)
    Notebooks and calendars
  - Diary, volumes I-V, 1916-1922 (Box 70)
  - Diary, volumes VI-VIII, 1922-1930 (Box 71)
  - Diary, volumes IX-XI, 1932-1940 (Box 72)
  - Diary, volumes XII-XIV, 1948 (Box 73)
  - Diary, volumes XV and indexes, 1951-1952 and undated (Box 74)
  - Photocopies of articles and books chiefly on American and newspaper history, 1918-1946 and undated, (54 items) (Box 75)
    Selected pages with Ball's annotations were photocopied. Arranged in rough chronological order by date of publication.
  - The Brass Check [hard-bound book] by Upton Sinclair (with Ball's annotations) (Box 75)
  - News is What We Make It [hard-bound book] by Kenneth Stewart (with Ball's annotations) (Box 75)
  - The Industrial Revolution in the South [hard-bound book] by Broadus and George Sinclair Mitchell (with Ball's annotations) (Box 75)
  - Additional correspondence, 1900-1952 and undated, (9 folders) (Box 76)
- Volumes, 1893-1951, (12 items)
  - Frank Parker: Digest of Military Service Record, 1894-1945 (Volume L:1312)
  - Account book, 1911-1915 (Volume F:6767)
  - Account book, 1916-1921 (Volume ff:6768)
  - Account book, 1921-1931 (Volume ff:6769)
  - Account book, 1932-1942 (Volume ff:6770)
  - Memorandum book, 1901 (Volume M:6771)
  - Scrapbook, 1893-1946 (Volume L:6772)
  - Scrapbook, 1895-1941 (Volume F:6773)
  - Scrapbook, 1909-1926 (Volume F:6774)
  - Scrapbook, 1910-1930 (Volume L:6775)
  - Scrapbook, 1915-1932 (Volume L:6776)
  - Scrapbook, 1939-1951 (Volume F:6777)
- Oversize Photographs, 1926, 1940, (2 items)
  - Panoramic group photo, Publishers and Editors of the U.S. Tour of New Hampshire, Navy Yard, Portsmouth, [New Hampshire], July 17, 1926 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Panoramic group photo, 53rd Convention Protestant Episcopal Church, Municipal Auditorium, Kansas City, [Missouri], October 9-24, 1940 (Opaperfolder 1)